A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Division (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Program Officer, Office Files of Michael Lipsky FA595
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Division (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Program Officer, Office Files of Michael Lipsky
1959-2003
Rockefeller Archive Center
Lipsky, Michael
Ford Foundation
FA595
22.5 Cubic Feet 59 containers
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Michael Lipsky's material arrived at the RAC in four accessions between 2012 and 2019.
The material that arrived in 2012 was originally processed into two collections, FA595 and FA725.
FA725 was originally part of Accession 2012:064, a large accession of Ford papers that was broken into many discrete collections. The original box numbers associated with this collection were Boxes 43107, 43111, 43124-43129, 43138-43143, and 43308. FA725 contained correspondence, reports, and state, city and project files. This collection was minimally processed and contained no series, file-level numbering, or biographical note.
FA595 originated from Accession 2012:044, another large accession that was broken into discrete collections. The collection's original box numbers were Boxes 48537-48543. FA595 contained four series: Correspondence, Program files (regional files and subject files), Innovations in State and Local Government files, and Program Related Investment (PRIs) and Finance Related Files. This collection was also minimally processed. Two more accessions of Michael Lipsky's material arrived in 2019 as Accession 2019:144 (Box 42604) and Accession 2019:145 (Box 42605). Accession 2019:145 contained files related to the Innovations in State and Local Government awards and were added to Series 4. Accession 2019:144 was added to Series 6: Subject Files.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Biographical / Historical
Michael Lipsky was a program officer at the Ford Foundation from 1991 until 2002. Between 1991 and 1995, Lipsky served as a program officer within the Ford Foundation's Governance and Public Policy unit. In 1996, after some restructuring at the Foundation, he was a program officer in the Peace and Social Justice within the Governance and Civil Society unit, and in 1997, he was promoted to Senior Program Officer. He left the Foundation in 2002.
One of Lipsky's primary responsibilities at the Foundation in the 1990s was organizing the Innovations in American Government program along with the Kennedy School of Government at Harvard University and the Council for Excellence in Government in Washington, D.C. The objective of the program was to demonstrate that American governments are capable of responding creatively and effectively to critical social issues. Each winning program received a Foundation grant of $100,000 to disseminate information about the program and encourage its replication. In 1995, the Foundation expanded the number of $100,000 awards to 15 and began honoring federal Innovations as well. The program was renamed Innovations in American Government at this time. Lipsky also worked on a similar program, the Partnership for Trust in Government. Founded in 1997, the Partnership convened 36 major American corporations, nonprofits and media organizations to promote the importance and accomplishments of government of the American people. The Partnership was managed by the Council for Excellence in Government. Lipsky was also involved in adapting the model of the Innovations program for government grantees in Brazil, the Philippines, South Africa, Chile, and Native American nations.
In addition to these activities, Lipsky was active in carrying out the State Fiscal Analysis Initiative. At the time of his involvement, SFAI was a network of 22 state-based organizations and several national nonprofits that produced timely and accessible state tax budget analysis in order to improve outcomes for low-income and other vulnerable populations. A similar program supported by Lipsky's work was Collaborations that Count, an eleven-state initiative in the South and Northwest to improve the ability of grassroots organizations to work together on a common agenda, and to work more effectively with policy analysis organizations. Lipsky also helped administer the Budget and Fiscal Analysis Network. In collaboration with the International Budget Project of the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities of Washington, D.C., program officers and grantees of the Foundation's overseas offices worked to advance budget transparency and accountability worldwide. Before leaving the Foundation, Lipsky worked to establish Leadership for a Changing World, a program to recognize and celebrate the contributions of community leaders in the United States. The first awards took place in 2001.
Before joining the Ford Foundation as a program officer in 1991, Lipsky was a temporary assistant in the Public Affairs Program at the Ford Foundation in 1965, an assistant professor of political science at the University of Wisconsin, and a professor of political science at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology from 1969-1991. He is known for writing Street-Level Bureaucracy, first published in 1980. Lipsky defined street-level bureaucrats as "public service workers who interact directly with citizens in the course of their jobs, and who have substantial discretion in the execution of their work."
After leaving the Foundation, Lipsky was senior program director of Demos, a non-partisan public policy research and advocacy organization, and an affiliate professor at Georgetown University.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 6 series:
1. Correspondence, 1991-2002
2. Country Files, 1991-2002
3. State Fiscal Analysis Initiative, 1991-2003
4. Innovations in State and Local Government Files, 1985-2003
5. Program Related Investment (PRIs) and Finance Related Files, 1959-1995
6. Subject Files, 1965-2002
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation's Governance and Public Policy Program (GPP) operated during the early to mid-1990s. It oversaw grants for programs and projects involved with citizen participation and electoral politics, policy think tanks and interdisciplinary approaches to economic and social policy, improving state and local government, increasing the number of minorities in the public policy field, and philanthropy and the nonprofit sector. GPP grantees included the Woodrow Wilson Program, the Innovations in American Government Awards Program, and the Public Agenda Foundation among many others. Jan Jaffe served as Acting Director for the program during a transition period between 1992 and 1993. June Zeitlin then became Director in 1993 and continued to lead the program when it transitioned to become the Governance and Civil Society Program in 1996. The Governance and Civil Society program's overarching goals were to improve governmental performance and accountability, find new approaches to implement public policies, and enhance the role of civic organizations in promoting democratic values.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents Michael Lipsky's work as a program officer for the Ford Foundation in the fields of governance, civil society, and peace and social justice. In particular, the collection highlights Lipsky's leading role in organizing the Innovations in American Government awards program from 1991-2001. Records related to the program include correspondence with government officials, reports, publications, application materials, and event materials. Another program established by Lipsky's work with the Foundation was the State Fiscal Analysis Initiative, a program to provide research, policy analysis, public education and coalition building for state budgets across the United States. The collection contains SFAI reports from state organizations, grant proposals, and correspondence.
More generally, trip reports, grant applications, and correspondence related to global and local governance initiatives can be found throughout the collection.
Federal government -- United States -- Awards; Ford Foundation; Government and Public Policy; Local government -- Awards; State Government -- United States -- Awards
- Correspondence, 1991-2002; 1
  Arrangement
  Chron files are arranged in yearly increments and then alphabetically by recipient's last name.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Michael Lipsky's correspondence with grantees, interoffice memos, and letters related to the organizational efforts behind Innovations in American Government events.
  - Chronological Correspondence, A-Z, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1-5, Box 2, Folder 6-10)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 12-14)
  - Chronological Correspondence, A-Z, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 15-16, Box 4, Folder 17-19)
  - Chronological Correspondence, A-Z, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 20-22, Box 5, Folder 23-24)
  - Chronological Correspondence, A-Z, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 25-28)
  - Chronological Correspondence, A-Z, 2000 January-May (Box 6, Folder 29-32)
  - Chronological Correspondence, A-Z, 2000 June-December (Box 6, Folder 33-35)
  - Chronological Correspondence (Karen Garcia's copies - Lipsky's assistant), 2000 (Box 7, Folder 36-37)
  - Chronological Correspondence, A-Z, 2001 January-July (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Chronological Correspondence, A-Z, 2001 July-December (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 40)
- Country Files, 1991-2002; 2
  Grant reviews, trip files, publications, notes from meetings, and reports related to Ford Foundation Governance and Civil Society grants in countries outside the United States.
  - Eastern Europe, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - East Africa, 1997-1999 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - East Africa Conference, 1994-1996 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Study on the Election of Villagers Committees in Rural China, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - The Report on the Villagers Representative Assemblies in China, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Colombia, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - CODESRIA, 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - India (Select materials related to Namibia and Eastern Europe), 1993-1999 (Box 8, Folder 48-49, Box 9, Folder 50-51)
  - Africa - Grants, Reports, Conference Materials, Background, etc., 1993-1994 (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - Asia, 1991-1994 (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - Mexico, 1993-1999 (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - Namibia - Decentralization in Namibia Summaries, 1997-1998 (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - Pakistan, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 56)
  - Philippines - Innovations and Excellence in Local Governance - Galing Pook Awards, 1995-1999 (Box 10, Folder 57)
  - Philippines - Manila Meeting Re: Innovations Awards, 1997 May 30-June 1 (Box 10, Folder 58)
  - Philippines - Memoranda, 1998-2000 (Box 10, Folder 59)
  - Poland - Exhibit Re: Innovations and Investments, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 60)
  - Poland - July 1998 Eastern Europe Trip, 1997-1998 (Box 10, Folder 61)
  - Senegal, 1993-1997 (Box 10, Folder 62)
  - South Africa - Innovations including Impumelelo Program, Grants, etc., 1995-1999 (Box 10, Folder 63)
  - West Africa - Dakar Visit, Reports, etc., 1994-1995 (Box 10, Folder 64)
  - India, 1994-1998 (Box 10, Folder 65-66, Box 11, Folder 67-68)
  - Israel, 1997-1999 (Box 11, Folder 69)
  - Kenya, 1993-1997 (Box 11, Folder 70)
  - Latin America, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 71)
  - Latin America (Governance), 1993 (Box 11, Folder 72)
  - Decentralized Governance in Asia, 1992-1993 (Box 11, Folder 73)
  - China, 1994-2000 (Box 11, Folder 74)
  - China Trip, 2000 September 4-12 (Box 11, Folder 75)
  - Brazil, 1991-1998 (Box 12, Folder 76)
  - Brazil Innovations Program, 1997-1998 (Box 12, Folder 77)
  - Chile, 1993-1998 (Box 12, Folder 78)
  - Australia, 1994-1996 (Box 12, Folder 79-80)
  - Bangladesh, 1992-1995 (Box 12, Folder 81)
  - Brazil and Brazil Notes, 1993-1999 (Box 12, Folder 82)
  - South Africa, 1993-1999 (Box 13, Folder 83-85)
  - India, 2001 (Box 13, Folder 86)
  - Nigeria - The Budget as a Tool for Ensuring Good Governance, 2000 December (Box 13, Folder 87)
  - China, 2001 (Box 13, Folder 88)
  - South Africa, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 89, Box 14, Folder 90)
  - Third International Conference (2012:064:001) (Box 13, Folder 89)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
  - South Africa - Impumelelo: Innovations Awards Programme, 2000 (Box 14, Folder 91)
  - Philippines, 1993-1999 (Box 14, Folder 92-95)
  - India - The Ford Foundation and Responsive Government in India, 2000 January (Box 15, Folder 96)
  - Uganda, 2000 (Box 15, Folder 97)
  - South Africa Report, 1996-2002 (Box 15, Folder 98-100)
  - Mexico File, 1999-2002 (Box 15, Folder 100-101)
- State Fiscal Analysis Initiative, 1991-2003; 3
  In 1993, the Ford Foundation joined with the Charles Stewart Mott Foundation and the Annie E. Casey Foundation to create the State Fiscal Analysis Initiative. The State Fiscal Analysis Initiative (SFAI) was created in response to social welfare responsibilities shifting from the national government to state and local governments. SFAI was a collaborative funding effort to empower state-level nonprofit organizations to undertake credible, timely and understandable analysis of critical budget and tax issues and inform the public on these matters. The Ford Foundation provided nearly half of the national foundation support for this initiative, which concluded in 2002. The grants supported research, policy analysis, public education and coalition building. Initially, grants averaged $100,000 annually for each state budget analysis project. The selected nonprofit affiliates were committed to addressing how budget issues were affecting low-income and disadvantaged groups in their states. SFAI supported 11 groups in 1993 to having affiliated policy groups in 29 states and the District of Columbia.
  SFAI grantees:
  Alabama Arise
  Arizona Children's Action's Alliance
  Georgians for Children
  Maine Center for Economic Policy
  Maine People's Resource Center
  Tax Equity Alliance for Massachusetts Education Fund
  North Carolina Legal Services Resource Center
  New York Fiscal Policy Institute
  Voices for Illinois Children
  Michigan League for Human Services
  Center for Public Policy Priorities in Texas
  University of Washington Institute for Public Policy Management
  National Organizations:
  Center on Budget and Policy Priorities
  Center for the Study of the States
  - DELTA Project - Mississippi Community Works HELP DESK, 1996-1999 (Box 15, Folder 102)
  - Mayfair Neighborhood Improvement Initiative, 1997 (Box 16, Folder 103)
  - Tennessee, 1998-2001 (Box 16, Folder 104)
    Council of Community Services
  - Alabama, 1998 (Box 16, Folder 105)
    Arise Citizens' Policy Project
  - Colorado, 2003 January (Box 16, Folder 106)
    Colorado Center on Law and Policy
  - Idaho, 1998-1999 (Box 16, Folder 107)
    Idaho Women's Network, Idaho Community Action Network, and United Vision for Idaho
  - Kentucky, 1998 (Box 16, Folder 108)
    Kentucky Coalition, The Kentucky Economic Justice Alliance
  - Oregon, 2000 (Box 16, Folder 109)
    Oregon Center for Public Policy, Rural Organizing Project
  - Oregon Trip, 1998 August 1 (Box 16, Folder 110)
  - Washington, 1998-1999 (Box 16, Folder 111)
    Washington Association of Churches, the Washington Citizen Action Education and Research Fund, and The Washington State Labor Council AFL-CIO
  - Minnesota, 1998 (Box 16, Folder 112)
  - Nevada, 1999 (Box 16, Folder 113)
    Progressive Leadership Alliance of Nevada (PLAN)
  - North Carolina, 1998 (Box 16, Folder 114)
    North Carolina Multi Issue Alliance, North Carolina Fund
  - USA (South), 1996-1998 (Box 16, Folder 115-116)
  - Texas, 1998 (Box 17, Folder 117)
    Southwest Regional Office of Consumers Union
  - Colorado, 2003 (Box 17, Folder 118-119)
    Colorado Progressive Coalition, Bell Policy Center, Colorado Fiscal Policy Institute
  - OMG Center for Collaborative Learning, 2002 (Box 17, Folder 120)
  - Arizona - Children's Action Alliance, 2002 (Box 17, Folder 121)
  - Michigan League for Human Services, 2002 (Box 17, Folder 122)
  - Voices for Illinois Children, 2002 (Box 17, Folder 123)
  - Alabama - Arise Citizens' Policy Project, 2002 (Box 17, Folder 124)
  - Maine Center for Economic Policy, 2002 (Box 17, Folder 125)
  - North Carolina Justice and Community Development Center for the Budget and Tax Center Project, 2002 (Box 17, Folder 126)
  - Idaho Center on Budget and Tax Policy, United Vision for Idaho, 2002 (Box 17, Folder 127)
  - Oregon Center for Public Policy, 2002 (Box 17, Folder 128)
  - Massachusetts - TEAM Education Fund, 2000 (Box 17, Folder 129)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative Responses to 9/11, 2001 (Box 17, Folder 130)
    State budget representatives responses to 10 questions from State Fiscal Analysis Initiative listserv
  - Arkansas Advocates for Children and Families, 2002 (Box 18, Folder 131)
  - Association for Children of New Jersey (ACNJ), 2002 (Box 18, Folder 132)
  - Wisconsin Council on Children and Families, 2002 (Box 18, Folder 133)
  - Colorado Center on Law and Policy, 2002 (Box 18, Folder 134)
  - Kentucky Youth Advocates, 2002 (Box 18, Folder 135)
  - New York - Fiscal Policy Institute, 2002 (Box 18, Folder 136)
  - North Carolina Budget and Tax Center - Community News (Grassroots Publication), 2002 June 14 (Box 18, Folder 137)
  - North Carolina Budget and Tax Center - Select News Clippings Citing Budget and Tax Center Staff, 2002 June 14 (Box 18, Folder 138)
  - North Carolina Budget and Tax Center - Budget and Tax Center Reports, 2002 June 14 (Box 18, Folder 139)
  - North Carolina Budget and Tax Center - Budget and Tax Center Special Reports, 2002 June 14 (Box 18, Folder 140)
  - North Carolina Budget and Tax Center - Select Budget and Tax Center Website Postings (Testimonies, Question and Answers, Fact Sheets, etc.), 2002 June 14 (Box 18, Folder 141)
  - North Carolina Budget and Tax Center - Various Budget and Tax Center Presentations, 2002 June 14 (Box 18, Folder 142)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative - Related Documents, 1993-1999 (Box 19, Folder 143-145)
  - New York - Fiscal Policy Institute, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 146)
  - Arizona - Children's Action Alliance, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 147)
  - LOGO/Improving Governance Memo, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 148)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative History, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 149)
  - Washington State, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 150)
    Washington Living Wage Movement
    Collaborations that Count
    Carolina Alliance for Fair Employment(?)
  - Workplan - Washington Living Wage Movement, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 151)
  - Innovations Scrapbook Summary Document, 1999 (Box 19, Folder 152)
  - Michael Lipsky's Program Officer Memo, 1999 (Box 19, Folder 153)
  - Seminars - E Government, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 154)
  - Montana - University of Montana, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 155)
  - Minnesota Nonprofit Association, 1998-2000 (Box 19, Folder 156)
  - Nevada - Progressive Leadership Alliance of Nevada, 2000-2001 (Box 19, Folder 157)
  - South Carolina - Fair Share Education Fund (Box 19, Folder 158)
  - Illinois - Voices for Illinois Children, 2001 (Box 19, Folder 159)
  - Role of the State, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 160)
  - Idaho, 2000-2001 (Box 19, Folder 161)
    Idaho Community Action Network, Idaho Women's Network, and United Visions for Idaho
  - Harvard University Project - Native American, 2000 (Box 19, Folder 162)
  - North Carolina Justice and Community Development Center, 2000-2002 (Box 19, Folder 163)
  - Contact Lists - State Organizations, 1999 (Box 19, Folder 164)
  - National Academy of Public Administration Letter, 2001 (Box 20, Folder 165)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative Proposals, 2000 (Box 20, Folder 166)
    North Carolina, Alabama, Oregon, Illinois, Maine, Arizona, Michigan
  - Thesis and Assessment - Implementing Policies within an Institutional Framework, Yvonne O Brunetto, 2000 (Box 20, Folder 167-169)
  - Mary Katzenstein papers, 1996-1997 (Box 20, Folder 170-171, Box 21, Folder 172)
    Protest Inside Institutions: Feminist Activism in the US Military and the American Catholic Church
    The Spectacle of Life and Death: Feminist and Lesbian/Gay Politics in the Military
    The Rebirth of Shiv Sena: The Symbiosis of Discursive and Organizational Power
    Stepsisters: Feminist Movement Activism in Different Institutional Spaces
  - Grant Materials and Correspondence, 1999-2001 (Box 21, Folder 173)
  - Presidents' Summit, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1997 April 27-29 (Box 21, Folder 174)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative - Guidance for Spring Site Visits, 1993-1994 (Box 21, Folder 175)
    Includes summary of visit to Georgians for Children
  - Spring Site Visit Reports (SFAI), 1994 (Box 21, Folder 176)
    Report on Site Visit to Children's Action Alliance (Arizona)
    Report on Site Visit to Georgians for Children
    Illinois Site Visit (Voices for Illinois Children)
    Site Visit Tax Equity Alliance for Massachusetts Education Fund (TEAM-ED)
    Michigan Site Visit - League for Human Services
    Site Visit to New York State Fiscal Analysis Initiative Grantee - Fiscal Policy Institute
    Site Visit to the North Carolina Legal Services Resource Center
    Center for Public Policy Priorities (Texas)
    Washington Site Visit (Grantee: Institute for Public Policy and Management/University of Washington)
    Site Visit Memo - Alabama Arise and Maine Center for Economic Policy
  - Classification of Lobbying Rules for State Fiscal Analysis Initiative Grantees, 1994 (Box 21, Folder 177)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative Meetings, 1993-1994 (Box 21, Folder 178)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative Mailings, 1994 (Box 21, Folder 179)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative Inquiries, 1993-1994 (Box 21, Folder 180)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative Consultant, Kay Sherwood, 1994 (Box 21, Folder 181)
  - State Fiscal Capacity Project Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 21, Folder 182, Box 22, Folder 183-184)
  - GrayHall, 1991-1993 (Box 22, Folder 185)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative Press Release, 1995 January 13 (Box 22, Folder 186)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative Texas Foundation Mailing and Responses, 1993-1994 (Box 22, Folder 187)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative Mailing and Responses, 1994 (Box 22, Folder 188)
  - State Fiscal Analysis RGA, 1994 (Box 22, Folder 189)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative Correspondence, 1994 (Box 22, Folder 190)
  - State Fiscal Analysis Initiative and Philanthropy Notes, 1994 January 27 (Box 22, Folder 191)
  - St. Paul, Minnesota Trip, 2000 (Box 22, Folder 192)
  - Susan V. Berresford Council Meeting Whitehead Forum, 1999 (Box 22, Folder 193)
  - Philadelphia, Pennsylvania Trip - "The State of State Constitutions," Rutgers University, Camden, 2000 (Box 22, Folder 194)
  - Akwasi Aidoo, 1994-1995 (Box 22, Folder 195)
  - David Arnold - India, 1994-1995 (Box 22, Folder 196)